Guide to the David Sullivan U.S. Maoism Collection TAM 527
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David Sullivan U.S. Maoism Collection
1918-2006
1970-1982
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
TAM 527
21.5 Linear Feet (24 boxes)
David Sullivan (19xx-2006) was active in the U.S. Maoist movement and collected organizational records, personal papers, printed ephemera, posters, and other materials pertaining thereto. He also became a repository for donations from individuals and organizations affiliated with the U.S. Marxist-Leninist-Maoist tradition. The collection contains materials that document what is referred to as the New Communist Movement. Segments of the collection pertain to the Revolutionary Union (RU), the Bay Area Revolutionary Union, the Revolutionary Communist Party (RCP), the Revolutionary Workers Headquarters (RWH), and the Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist) (CPML). The collection traces the internal debates of these organizations, their mergers and splits, as well as their organizational campaigns from the early 1970s through 1982. While it is unclear as to Sullivan's precise affiliation with these organizations, from the material present, it is certain that he was involved in union organizing with both the United Autoworkers and the United Steelworkers of America in the mid- to late 1970s. Subject files from various individuals highlight work with the National Lawyers Guild, Vietnam Veterans Against the War, and in struggles for women's rights. The collection also consists of a wide selection of both buttons and posters, which compliment the organizations represented in the collection's extensive series of printed ephemera from other U.S. Marxist-Leninist-Maoist organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Erika Sullivan and Molly Nestor in 2010. The accession number associated with this gift is 2010.021.
Arrangement
In Series I-IV, materials are divided by district, topic, and format and folders are arranged alphabetically. Series V is first divided by union, the United Autoworkers and the United Steelworkers of America, and then further by local, district, and/or topic. Folders are alphabetically arranged. Series VI: Subject Files is arranged alphabetically by subject. Series VII: Organizational Printed Ephemera is arranged alphabetically by organization. For Series VIII and IX, the buttons and posters are grouped either by organization or topic and then arranged alphabetically. The collection is arranged into 9 Series.
The collection is arranged into 9 Series. For Series I-IV, materials are divided by district, topic, and format and folders are arranged alphabetically. Series V is first divided by union, the United Autoworkers and the United Steelworkers of America, and then further by local, district, and/or topic. Folders are alphabetically arranged. Series VI: Subject Files is arranged alphabetically by subject. Series VII: Organizational Printed Ephemera is arranged alphabetically by organization. For Series VIII and IX, the buttons and posters are grouped either by organization or topic and then arranged alphabetically. Series X: Artifacts and Other Ephemera is arranged alphabetically by format.
Missing Title
Series I: Revolutionary Union, 1970-1978
Series II: Revolutionary Communist Party, 1975-1982
Series III: Revolutionary Workers Headquarters, 1977-1984
Series IV: Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist), 1976-1981
Series V: Union Organizing, 1961-1988
Series VI: Subject Files, 1938-1987
Series VII: Organizational Printed Ephemera, 1938-2006
Series VIII: Buttons, 1918-1984
Series IX: Posters, 1968-1990
Series X: Artifacts and Other Ephemera, 1965-1993
Historical/Biographical Note
David Sullivan (19xx-1006) spent his youth engaged in progressive and radical politics in New York City. His parents were both liberal Democrats and his father was a professor of Psychology at New York University. Sullivan attended PS 41 for junior high and enrolled in high school on the Lower East Side of Manhattan at Seward Park High School; he was an activist in both schools. During high school, the anti-Vietnam war movement was ablaze in New York City and around the country. Sullivan considered himself on the left-wing, anti-imperialist end of the movement. In 1967 when Martin Luther King Jr. spoke at Riverside Church in New York, Sullivan was a marshal for the 5th Avenue Peace Parade Committee. He affiliated himself with the Youth Against War and Fascism and helped to found the Seward Park Peace and Freedom Coalition. Sullivan was also active in the high school student union and published a student paper. Additionally, he acted as a "scout" during the Spring Mobilization for Peace activities of 1968, where he rode his bike around Washington Square Park and used pay phones to spread information on the whereabouts of the police. Sullivan was eventually arrested in Washington Square.
When King was assassinated in April 1968, Sullivan was attending an anti-war meeting. He immediately produced a leaflet in support of the MLK memorial and organized students at his school to go. Sullivan marched to the principle's office demanding that the school be shut down for the memorial. When the principle declined, the students marched out anyway. Sullivan continued to be involved in radical politics throughout his time in high school. Acting as part of a liberated school at Seward Park that was established during the Teacher's Union strike of 1969, Sullivan was arrested again.
David Sullivan attended college in Yellow Springs, Ohio at Antioch College. He was involved with Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) and continued to be an anti-war, anti-imperialist activist. Sullivan, however, like many students grew disillusioned with the youth movement and turned to the teachings of Marx, Lenin, and Mao. SDS was going through massive splits at the time. One splinter group of SDS was the Revolutionary Youth Movement II, known as RYM-II. RYM-II eventually fractured into two major groups, one led by Mike Klonsky was the October League, the other led by Bob Avakian was known as the Bay Area Revolutionary Union.
The David Sullivan U.S. Maoism Collection consists of the internal and public documents of four organizations central to the Marxist-Leninist tradition in the United States: the Revolutionary Union, the Revolutionary Communist Party, The Revolutionary Workers Headquarters, and the Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist). Sullivan was involved with the groups following his work with SDS at Antioch. These organizations have origins in the student activism of the late 1960s. The relationships between the four organizations are filled with splits and mergers, which are outlined throughout the collection.
The origins of the Revolutionary Union (RU) lay with the formation of the Bay Area Revolutionary Union (BARU) in 1968 by Bob Avakian and Steve Hamilton. BARU had units in San Francisco, Oakland-Berkeley, Richmond, and Palo Alto, California. The group initiated the Richmond Workers Committee, which played a support role during the Standard Oil strike of 1969. In the early 1970s, the BARU wanted to grow into a larger, more nationalized organization and went on a United States tour to gain membership. Sullivan found out about the RU through this tour; he joined a collective of the Revolutionary Union in Ohio circa the early 1970s. Sullivan then went to work for ALCOA Steel Corporation in Cleveland as part of his work with the RU.
The Revolutionary Union in the East Coast helped to form the November 4th Coalition, which organized an anti-imperialist demonstration in New York City in 1973. The RU also helped to run a workers conference the following year in March. The group continued to act throughout the 1970s, for instance on campaigns against Nixon, such as the "Throw the Bum Out" campaign, but also on the national energy crisis and with postal workers in an organization called Outlaw.
The RU, through its district and national bulletins, focused on developing a central task for the organization. The Revolutionary Union was concerned not only with developing this central task but also the methodology through which it was achieved. Through these bulletins the RU wrote extensively on summing up campaigns and putting forth political lines. Important issues for the Revolutionary Union included trade union organizing, black liberation, the national question, the international situation, and building a United Front Against Imperialism. They produced the widely circulated Red Papers, which functioned as a theoretical journal for Marxist-Leninists.
In 1975, the Revolutionary Union founded the Revolutionary Communist Party (RCP). This new formation was in line with the Union's central task of party building. Bob Avakian continued to be a leading figure within the RCP. The RCP supported the domestic and foreign policies of the People's Republic of China until Mao's death in 1976. They opposed what they saw as revisionist, social imperialist policies of the Soviet Union.
Two years after the 1976 overthrow of the Gang of Four in China, the RCP split. The majority, led by Avakian, felt that the Chinese government had adopted revisionist policies, while the minority, which supported the present regime of the Chinese Communist Party, established the Revolutionary Workers Headquarters.
In the mid-1970s, the Party opposed busing, affirmative action, and black nationalism, believing them to be non-revolutionary policies. To demonstrate against U.S. expansionist policies they briefly occupied the Alamo. They were instrumental in the organization of the National United Workers Organization and the Unemployed Workers Organizing Committee. In the late 1970s, the RCP shifted its concentration from heavy industry toward youth and immigrant workers. In 1982, after a three-year court battle, 17 members, the Mao Tsetung Defendants, were acquitted of felony charges for alleged violence at a demonstration in Washington, D.C. In 1989 the RCP won a supreme court ruling that flag burning falls under protection of the first amendment. Since 1975, they have published The Worker.
The Revolutionary Workers Headquarters (RWH) formed a minority faction within the RCP, disagreeing with leadership in the RCP over the politics and policies of the Chinese Communist Party. The RWH officially separated from the RCP in 1977, as announced in their publication, Voices of the Rebellion. The RWH was involved in much the same struggles as the RCP, concerned with organizing workers and the unemployed, and forming an anti-imperialist revolutionary organization. They too focused on the national question and the international situation. Much of their work, as reflected in the material, pertained to uniting Marxist-Leninists, believed to be a central task of revolutionaries. They had merger negotiations with the Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist), the Proletarian Unity League, the Bay Area Communist Union, and the League of Revolutionary Struggle.
The Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist) (CPML), originally known as the October League, was founded in 1971. Michael Klonsky, active with Students for a Democratic Society, was a primary figure of the CPML. The Party published the influential and widely read newspaper, The Call. The central task of the October League was party building and uniting Marxist-Leninists in a united front against imperialism. They engaged in lengthy merger talks with the Revolutionary Workers Headquarters during the late 1970s and into the 1980s.
David Sullivan, though not directly involved with every organization represented in the collection, became a repository for materials related to the Marxist-Leninist-Maoist tradition. Various individuals and organizations donated their papers to him. These, along with material he created and collected, make up the bulk of the collection.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Revolutionary Communist Party Records (TAM 090)
Revolutionary Workers Headquarters Records (TAM 244)
Scope and Content Note
The David Sullivan U.S. Maoism Collection contains internal material and printed ephemera documenting the Marxist-Leninist-Maoist tradition in the United States. Four groups central to the milieu, and whose material is heavily represented in the collection are the Revolutionary Union (RU), the Revolutionary Communist Party (RCP), the Revolutionary Workers Headquarters (RWH), a breakaway faction of the RCP, and the Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist) (CPML). Each of these organizations produced district and national bulletins, fliers, and other printed material that can be found in the collection. Throughout Series I-IV, which document these four organizations are internal materials related to pertinent debates, including folders on the international situation and the Gang of Four in China following the death of Mao Tsetung in 1976, party building, revisionism, and trade union strategies. Also included is correspondence between the organizations on their various efforts to unite all Marxist-Leninists. The Collection also contains a sizable amount of printed and other ephemera from hundreds of leftist organizations. In addition to brochures, fliers, pamphlets, and publications, there are also buttons and posters. The organizations are wide ranging from local event based coalitions to national groups like the Black Workers Congress and the Communist Party of the USA, generally these organizations are U.S. based.
Separated Materials
Runs of periodicals and books were separated to the Tamiment Library print department.
Communists |z Illinois |z Chicago.; Communists -- United States.; Pamphlets.; Political posters, American.; Maoist parties |z United States.; Communism -- China.; Communism |z Illinois |z Chicago.; Maoism -- United States.; Communism -- United States.; Communist parties |z United States.; Bulletins.; Buttons (information artifacts).; China -- Politics and government.; Communism.; Labor movement -- United States.; Labor movement.; Labor Day.; Agendas (administrative records); Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Labor unions -- Elections.; Labor union democracy.; Labor unions and communism.; Labor unions -- Political activity -- United States.; May Day.; Labor unions -- Elections -- United States.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; New Left -- United States.; Unemployed -- United States.; Unemployment |z United States.; Printed ephemera.; Posters.; National Lawyers Guild; Sullivan, David; Revolutionary Union; Revolutionary Workers Headquarters of the RCP; Mao, Zedong, 1893-1976.; Revolutionary Communist Party, USA; United Steelworkers of America; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; Nestor, Molly; Sullivan, Erika
- Series I: Revolutionary Union, 1970-1978
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I contains material generated by and about the Revolutionary Union and its local collectives, including the leading Bay Area Revolutionary Union. The material ranges in date from 1970-1978 and is divided by committee, local, district, and regional, as well as by subject and format. While a portion of this Series is printed and public and includes calendars, fliers, national and district bulletins, pamphlets and publications, a majority is internal. There are drafts of the Revolutionary Union's theoretical paper, Red Papers 5 and 6 as well as position papers on factionalism and developing the political line of the working class. Of note are folders concerning among other things: the expulsion from the Revolutionary Union of Bruce Franklin, his wife Jane Franklin, and Janet Weiss, a history of the East Coast Regional, and correspondence regarding the RU's security measures and stance on gay liberation. There are also folders with material about the Revolutionary Union's stance on the 1972 McGovern Presidential campaign, as well as their positions on party building, democratic centralism, and recruitment. Material pertaining to the Revolutionary Union's political campaigns surrounding farm workers, international women's day, may day, students, tenants, trade unions, the unemployed, and veterans is evident in this Series.
  - Anti-Repression Campaign, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Attica Brigade, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bay Area Revolutionary Union, 1970-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bay Area Revolutionary Union: Women's Commission, circa 1969 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Bay Area Worker Investigation, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Black Cadre, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Black Liberation, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bulletins: District, circa 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bulletins: National, circa 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bulletins: "On the Final Phases of Forming the Party", undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Calendar (workers' history), 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Central Committee, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Central Committee: "Forging a Fighting Revolutionary Organization", undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Central Committee: Party Building, circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Central Task, Developing of, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chile, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cleveland, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Community Work (chronology), circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence (security) (homosexual paper), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Criticism of: "The 'Two Stages' Thesis in the American Revolution", undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - December 15th Demonstration (energy), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Democratic Centralism, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Draft Programme for the Party of the U.S. Working Class, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - East Coast Region, History of, circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Energy Crisis, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Expulsions (DH Wright), undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Expulsions (Franklin group), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Farmworkers, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Fliers, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Files on Revolutionary Union/Revolutionary Communist Party I, 1980, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Files on Revolutionary Union/Revolutionary Communist Party II, 1980, undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Homosexuality and Gay Liberation, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Intermediate Workers Organizations (IWOs), undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - International Women's Day, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Jersey City Collective, undated (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Joint Committee: Friendship Fair and October 1st Celebration Activities, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Left Adventurism (expulsion of Franklin, et al), undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Los Angeles Collective, Criticism of Revolutionary Union, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Marxist-Leninist Study Group, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - May Day, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - McGovern, George Campaign, circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - National Caucus of Labor Committees, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - National Central Committee (NCC), undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - National Central Committee (NCC): Main Political Report, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - National Secretariat, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Newspaper, Discussion about, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - NY-NJ, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - October League, Tactical Line on, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - On the Move (organization and newspaper), 1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Outlaw (postal workers), undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Pamphlets, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Pamphlets, 1972, undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Party Building, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Party Building: Program Discussion Committees, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Political Education, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Political Struggle, Definition of, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Position Paper: "Develop the Political Struggle of the Working Class", undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Position Paper: "Factionalism", undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Position Papers and Reports (various), 1970-1971, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Prairie Fire (song group), undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Propaganda, undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Publications about, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Reading, Pennsylvania: Position Paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - RCC (?) Meeting, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Recruitment, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Red Papers 5: Draft I, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Red Papers 5: Draft II, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Red Papers 6, Criticism of, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Red Papers 6: Draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - "Report on the Ideological Struggle", undated (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Reports, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Reports: District, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Resignation Letters, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Revolution, Material Related to, 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Revolution: Reprints, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - RU Women for Liberation, undated (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Santa Clara County Workers' Committee (CA), undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Second Center Line, undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Security, undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Speech regarding (by Steve Hamilton), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Standing Committee: Draft Political Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Standing Committee: Regional, undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Standing Committee: Reports, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Teachers Guide to Marxist-Leninist Fundamentals Study Group, undated (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Tenants Work, circa 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Third World Liberation/ National Question, undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Throw the Bum Out Demonstration (Nixon), undated (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Trade Union Work, undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Trenton Area, undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Unemployed Workers' Organizing Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Veterans, undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Western New York District, circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Women's Caucus, undated (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Women's Commission, undated (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - The Worker, Material Related to, undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Young Communist League, undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Young Lords Party, Report from Attending Congress of, undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Youth/ Student Work I, undated (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Youth/ Student Work II, undated (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Youth/ Student Work III, undated (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Youth/ Student Work IV, undated (Box 23, Folder 17)
- Series II: Revolutionary Communist Party, 1975-1982
  Series II contains material generated by and about the Revolutionary Communist Party and dates from the Party's founding in 1975 up through 1982. Material is divided by committee and district as well as topic and format. While a portion of this Series is printed and public, including district and national bulletins, constitutions, fliers, pamphlets, and publications, it largely consists of internal documents. Folders contain drafts and memos on central topics such as busing, China and the Gang of Four, Iran, political education, students, and trade union organizing. Of note are folders containing material related to the founding congress, including committee reports and resolutions as well as main political reports, the split with the Revolutionary Workers Headquarters, and speeches from the Mao Tsetung Memorial in 1976. Material from the Revolutionary Communist Party's political work surrounding International Women's Day, the July 4th Bicentennial, and May Day is represented in this Series with fliers, drafts, and political reports. There is also material related to the RCP's involvement in organizing with the National United Workers Organization, the Unemployed Workers Organizing Committee, and the Vietnam Veterans Against the War.